An Annotated Calendar of the Letters of Charles Darwin in the Library of the American Philosophical Society 1799-1882 Mss.B.D25
American Philosophical Society
An Annotated Calendar of the Letters of Charles Darwin in the Library of the American Philosophical Society
1799-1882
Mss.B.D25
American Philosophical Society
2.5 Linear feet
One of the most important natural historians in nineteenth century Britain, Charles Darwin provided the first compelling mechanism to account for organismal evolutionary change. Although lacking a coherent model of heredity, Darwin's natural selection has exerted an enormous influence over the biological sciences and since the introduction of Mendelian genetics, had remained the key unifying principle in the discipline. The APS Darwin Papers are a large a valuable assemblage of Darwin's correspondence with scientific colleagues, including Charles Lyell and George J. Romanes. They are included in the print version of the Correspondence of Charles Darwin (Cambridge Univ. Press).
2.5 linear feet
Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882
Biographical/Historical note
The profound influence of the thought of Charles Darwin on contemporary scientific culture stems largely from his theory of natural selection, the first widely accepted mechanism to account for organismal evolutionary change. A product of Victorian preconceptions of the order of nature and the nature of change, both Darwin and his theories have proven remarkably resilient and remain a vital heuristic in the biological sciences.
The son of the physician Robert Darwin, Charles Darwin was blessed with a pair of illustrious grandfathers from the progressive elite of British Whiggery, the savant and proto-evolutionist, Erasmus Darwin, and the manufacturer of ceramics, Josiah Wedgwood. Born in Shrewsbury on February 12, 1809, Charles entered the University of Edinburgh at age sixteen, intending to follow in his father's footsteps into medicine, but he proved as unmotivated a student as he was unenthusiastic. Repulsed by the experience of attending surgeries undertaken in the absence of anaesthetics, Darwin abandoned his already half-hearted commitment to medicine and in 1827, he left Edinburgh for Christ's College, Cambridge, to study for the ministry.
The change of venue did little to rouse Darwin's enthusiasm for coursework, however at Cambridge, he met three men whose enthusiasm for nature sparked his imagination. With the great geologist, Charles Lyell, Darwin undertook field excursions to south Wales and was introduced to the concept of uniformitarianism; with F.W. Hope, he spent the summer of 1829 collecting bugs and beetles; while the botanist John Stevens Henslow encouraged his interest in the natural sciences, but equally importantly introduced him to Captain Robert Fitz-Roy. After receiving his degree in 1831, Darwin signed on as naturalist aboard Fitz-Roy's H.M.S. Beagle on its cruise around the world. Summarizing Darwin's subsequent career would be an exercise in courting claims to insufficiency while guaranteeing inadequacy, yet
Returning home from the Beagle in 1836, Darwin began in earnest to write and publish in natural history. His first paper, speculating on the origin of coral atolls, was begun in December 1835, and he began his first notebook on theories relating to the transmutation of species in July 1837, only two months after presenting his coral atoll paper at the Geological Society. Financial pressures were not a concern for the well-heeled Darwin, particularly after marrying his wealthy first cousin, Emma Wedgwood, in January 1839, and from the late 1830s onward, Darwin was able to lead an gentleman's life devoted to the pursuit of science, interrupted on occasion by illness and family concerns.
Darwin's first major monograph, his Journal of Researches (London: H. Colburn, 1839), was an important record of the geological and natural historical observations made during his voyage aboard the Beagle, and was a huge popular success. Since his visit to the Galapagos aboard the Beagle, however, Darwin had been percolating with ideas on the transmutation of species, an idea that had concerned his grandfather Erasmus before him. According to Darwin's retelling of the events, his ideas began to gel after reading Thomas Malthus's Essay on the Principle of Population, which confirmed his predilection for viewing nature as a struggle for existence in which "favourable variations would tend to be preserved and unfavourable ones to be destroyed." Malthusian logic, he believed, would lead one to conclude that the end result would be the differential reproduction of animal populations based upon the characteristics each possessed, leading ultimately to speciation. By the early 1840s, Darwinian natural selection was beginning to germinate.
Yet still he sat. Darwin's research during the 1840s and early 1850s included brushes with the evolutionist thought of the botanist J.D. Hooker, the cosmic Robert Chambers and others, and in 1842, he sketched out the rudiments of his theory, thinking enough of it to have it copied two years later. His ardor for publishing on the topic may have been cooled by the hostility he saw meted out to Chambers' Vestiges of the Natural Creation (1844), but his attention was also divided -- barnacles and migraines were as much part of Darwin's decades as natural selection. Even the appearance in 1855 of Alfred Russel Wallace's "On the Law Which has Regulated the Introduction of New Species" in the Annals and Magazine of Natural History did little to prod Darwin onward, nor did the intervention of his old mentor, Charles Lyell, speed the pen. It was not until 1858 that Darwin moved forward, having receiving a letter from Wallace informing him that Malthus's Essay had illuminated his thinking on the origin of species, and enclosing a manuscript for comment that outlined a theory with a strong, coincidental resemblance to Darwin's own. Fearful of losing any claim to priority, Darwin had his 1844 essay and Wallace's published jointly in the Journal of the Proceedings of the Linnean Society in August 1858, and he proceeded feverishly (often literally so) to work on a longer "abstract" of his ideas, the work that became his magnum opus, On the Origin of Species (London: J. Murray, 1859).
In the spectacular sequence of books that followed, Darwin elucidated various aspects of the theory of natural selection, progressing with increasing confidence through The Variation of Animals and Plants Under Domestication (London: J.Murray, 1868), The Descent of Man and Selection in Relation to Sex (London: J. Murray, 1871); and The Expression of the Emotions in Man and the Animals (London: J. Murray, 1872). Lacking, as he admitted, in any coherent theory of heredity, Darwin's natural selection nevertheless provided a persuasive explanation of the mechanics of organismal change. While the response to natural selection was not uniformly warm, perhaps even providing impetus to Lamarckian theories of inheritance, it was chiefly responsible for establishing evolutionary change as an integral part of biological explanation. The broader implications of Darwin's thought, including the role of contingency, relativism, and stochasticity in organismal change continue to define biological interests. More subtly, his ideas catalyzed a slow shift away from typological thinking (imaging the organism with respect to a perfect "type") toward viewing organisms in the context of a population, an attitudinal adjustment with profound implications for the practice of science in the twentieth century.
Darwin continued with research and writing until the time of his death on April 19, 1882. His last work was the quirky, fascinating, and perhaps prophetic book, The Formation of Vegetable Mould Through the Action of Worms (London: J. Murray 1882).
Scope and Contents note
Much of the text for this finding aid has been taken from the printed volume, Calendar of Darwin Letters in the American Philosophical Society by P. Thomas Carroll.
The Darwin Papers at the American Philosophical Society represent approximately 15% of the surviving correspondence of the British evolutionary theorist, Charles Darwin. Consisting chiefly of correspondence between Darwin and other scientists writing on subjects from natural selection and the theory of evolution to the controversy caused by On the Origin of Species, the Darwin Papers.
The earliest accession of Darwin Papers at the APS consisted of an extensive and important series of letters between Darwin and his colleague and mentor, Charles Lyell, that frame the development of their thought from the late 1830s into the 1870s. There is a wealth of other important correspondence in the collection with John Thomas Gulick, George John Romanes, and Philip Lutley Sclater, among others.
This collection includes photostats of letters from Walsh to Darwin, in the Chicago Museum of Natural History, and photostats of Darwin manuscripts in possession of Dr. Robert M. Stecher, Cleveland, Ohio.
Relevance of the Darwin Calendar
Thousands of pages have been written about Charles Robert Darwin (1809-1882), whose Origin of Species laid the foundation for modern evolutionary theory. Even so, our picture of Darwin and our assessment of his place in history are undergoing constant revision. Relatively speaking, we are, after all, only recently accustomed to the notion that we share a common ancestry with apes, and few outside the biological professions yet appreciate the sweeping implications of population thinking (as opposed to typological thinking) or the concept of ecology. The social and political significance of Darwin's work will probably be debated for some time to come. Many historians of science are interested in the processes by which Darwin's ideas were formulated, disseminated, and ultimately accepted by scientists and by laymen. Scientists continue to be enlightened by reading Darwin 1 and publication of transcriptions of Darwin's various manuscripts occurs regularly. 2
Given these developments, as well as the added stimulus provided by the 1959 centennial of the publication of the Origin, it seems certain that research and writing upon Darwin will continue, with scholars demanding access to ever more records of Darwin's life and work. This calendar was prepared with this demand in mind, so that readers may better interpret the significance of this great naturalist's achievements and those of his colleagues.
The five remaining sections of this introduction explain in a general way the design and the intended utility of the calendar. They discuss the following topics: 1)the primary importance of letters in the assessment of Darwin's life and work; 2) the justification for publishing these letters; 3) the nature of the Darwin letters collection at the Library of the American Philosophical Society; 4) the reasons for publishing the letters in the more-or-less unfashionable calendar format; and 5) the unique problems encountered in dating the letters. A rather extensive and detailed statement of the editorial method employed in this calendar follows the introduction.
Darwin's Letters
Modern man, armed with the telephone and often inundated with bureaucratic paperwork, might find it hard to comprehend how important letters were to life among the literate elite of the nineteenth century, and how valuable these nineteenth-century letters now are to scholars. But Darwin's contemporaries knew well the value of letters; Thomas Jefferson put the point succinctly in 1823 when he argued that "the letters of a person, especially of one whose business has been chiefly transacted by letters, form the only full and genuine journal of his life." 3 This was especially true of scientists and other scholars of the day, for whom communication of the written word was such an integral part of intellectual activity.
Letters are particularly significant in Darwin's case. Physically isolated at Down House for most of his life and often immobilized by chronic illness, Darwin depended more heavily than others upon letters as his principal mode of communication. Moreover, because correspondence was Darwin's usual medium of contact with his closest friends, his letters often exhibit a degree of candor about his life and work not revealed clearly in any of his other papers and publications -- not even in the intimate Autobiography which, though written for his own satisfaction and the entertainment of his children, lacked the presence of daily communication and was tempered somewhat by the restraints of Darwin's time and class. 4
Finally, the unusually heterogeneous quality of the Darwin letters reveal better than any other of the records of his life the diversity of his daily routine and the catholicity of his interests and preoccupations.
Scholars who examine the record of Darwin's life contained in his letters can expect to find many types of information. For the historian of science with a bent toward the history of ideas, there is abundant material on Darwin's scientific views. Sometimes a passage in a letter clarifies or corrects a claim in one of Darwin's published works; for example, in a letter to Charles Lyell in 1860, Darwin is tempering a rather extreme contention, which he had written into the Origin, when he writes that "Ammonites have become wholly extinct in a remarkably sudden manner relatively to most other families [and not absolutely, as implied in the Origin]; I meant only this [in the Origin], but I see I have not been nearly guarded enough." 5 At other times Darwin retracts assertions made in previous letters; in some cases only the earlier, unamended claim has been published, so that the unsuspecting scholar may be misled if he does not peruse carefully the unpublished materials. 6
Occasionally, a Darwin letter will contain opinions and theories not yet expressed in print, or at least not yet expressed as well as in the particular unpublished letter at hand; writing to Lyell in 1860, for example, Darwin argued that "how far to lump & split species is indeed a hopeless problem. It must in the end, I think, be determined by mere convenience." 7 It would be hard to locate a more succinct or more modern expression of Darwin's well-known disbelief in the existence of identifiable species.
Scholars interested in the social history of science, the growth of scientific ideas, the sociology of science, and the dynamics of scientific communities also will find much of interest in the letters, for they contain many of Darwin's views on these subjects, especially in reference to Darwin's assessment of the prospects for ultimate acceptance of his own theories. This is best exemplified in Darwin's confidences to friends in 1859 and 1860 regarding the fate of the Origin, 8 but there are other examples concerning Darwin's views about priority and his estimation of the role his cirripede work would play in the growth of science. 9
Still another revealing type of information expressed only in the letters is that relating to Darwin's assessments of his colleagues -- enlightening glimpses of Darwin's critical insight at work which rarely surfaced in the polite society of contemporary England but are now absolutely necessary for a full understanding of his professional identity and behavior. Where else can one find Darwin saying of Robert FitzRoy: "I never cease wondering at his character,... full of good... traits but spoiled by such an unlucky temper. Some part of... his brain wants mending....?" 10. It is no wonder that this passage, as well as one which describes Richard Owen as "wonderfully clever in his malevolence," 11 usually were deleted silently from the earlier published versions of Darwin's letters -- this is all the more reason for including them here.
To complement such insights and revelations, there is much autobiographical matter in the letters. It might be used to construct a reasonably good record both of Darwin's face-to-face encounters with his colleagues and of the content of such meetings. 12 Often the letters record Darwin's whereabouts, which information is especially useful in determining the dates of Darwin's frequent one-day trips into London -- something not systematically recorded elsewhere. 13 Moreover, the letters constantly remind us that Darwin was as much a family man and a medical patient as he was a naturalist and a scientist, and they show how these different aspects of Darwin's life tended to interact. For example, in 1860, Darwin's daughter contracted remittent fever, and the family was forced by their concern for the young girl's life to remove to a healthier climate than that found at Down. While thus away, Darwin found himself unable to continue the research he had been conducting at home, so he filled his idle time by examining the sun-dew, an insectivorous plant common to the area being visited. This work eventually led to the publication of an entire book on insectivorous plants, and one could therefore argue the extreme externalist position that illness had been the cause for its appearance. 14
Still another type of correspondence consists of purely business letters, which range from orders and acknowledgments of books and reprints -- data valuable to scholars -- to routine details such as the addition of a wing to Down House in 1876-1877 or the purchase of medical supplies. 15 Such routine letters show, if nothing else, Darwin's meticulousness, and they are sometimes useful for dating other Darwin letters of greater import.
Need to Publish Letters
To a certain extent, scholars have been reaping benefits from Darwin's letters for long time, since the bulk of Darwin's most important letters have been in print for well over fifty years, and additional letters have been published from time to time ever since. 16 One might well ask, then, why a calendar of 700 more letters is necessary, especially since portions, at least, of roughly half of the letters in the American Philosophical Society's collection have already been printed. Several different responses can be given to this question.
Most importantly, there is the problem of selection criteria in the major published collections of Darwin's correspondence. The three works which contain published versions of many of the items calendared below (as well as a great many other Darwin letters) provide only a selection of Darwin's correspondence, and those letters which are included are usually not transcribed in full. In all three of these works, the choice of both which letters are to be included and which portions of the chosen letters are to be printed has been colored by the motives of the editors. As these motives are not those of historians today, there are limitations -- some of them severe -- to the usefulness of these works as definitive references for modern scholars. To illustrate the point: "In choosing letters for publication," says Darwin's son Francis in the opening line of the preface of his edition of his father's Life and Letters, " I have been largely guided by the wish to illustrate my father's personal character." In some cases, such guidance led him to give a relatively low priority to the illustration of Darwin's scientific work, and in most cases, it meant deleting family matters as well as derogatory remarks and other embarrassing details. 17 More Letters, edited by Francis Darwin and A. C. Seward, somewhat redresses the balance; its editors say that they prepared the volumes "to give as full an idea as possible of the course of Mr. Darwin's work," and they state further that their compendium contains "practically all the matter that it now seems desirable to publish. But," they continue, "at some future time others may find interesting data in what remains unprinted; this is certainly true of a short series of letters dealing with the Cirripedes, which are omitted solely for want of space." 18 Similarly, in the preface to her two-volume biography of her mother, which contains 66 of her father's letters, Darwin's daughter, H. E. Litchfield, confesses that she began to prepare a record of her mother's life because she thought it would be "of value to her [Emma Darwin's] grandchildren," and then she altered and enlarged the scope of the book as she became interested in "the personalities of the writers" of the letters printed therein. 19 While such criteria of inclusion and exclusion were perfectly respectable and common in their day, and scholars have profited greatly from all these works despite their limitations, there is still a need to treat Darwin's letters more systematically, particularly with the needs of historians of science and other scholars in mind.
A still more serious indictment of the principal sources of Darwin's correspondence is that those letters which do appear in them were not edited according to rigorous modern standards. "In printing the letters," Francis Darwin confesses about the Life and Letters, " I have followed (except in a few cases) the usual plan of indicating the existence of omissions or insertions." One wonders what the "few cases" were, and exactly how few they were. "I have not followed the originals," he continues, "as regards the spelling of names, the use of capital letters, or in the manner of punctuation." 20 Similarly, in More Letters, " dots indicate omissions, but many omissions are made without being so indicated." 21 In Emma Darwin, " many omissions are made without putting any sign that this has been done. Neither the punctuation nor the spelling has been rigidly followed. But the sense has never wittingly been altered, although occasionally a word evidently omitted has been added without putting any sign that this has been done." 22
In addition to the problems relating to the imprecise editorial standards of these works and to standards of letter selection which stress Darwin's character to the neglect of his career and other aspects of his life, some scholars may have difficulty in using these works because: the letters are not placed in chronological order; in far too many cases are incorrectly dated or are not dated at all 23; and the indexes are inadequate.
To a certain extent, these final criticisms can also be levelled at some of the small selections of Darwin letters published as journal articles with increasing frequency since the centennial of the publication of the Origin in 1859. 24 Moreover, the quality of the transcriptions in some of these articles is not very good. 25 While this calendar will not rectify all of these problems (most notably because it contains a rather small and arbitrary selection of those letters published in these articles), it should clarify all such problems for the letters with which it deals. Moreover, use of this calendar should at least streamline the kind of research which can be conducted only while one is visiting the Society's archives. This should save much research time. 26
Nature of the Society's Darwin Collections
To a first approximation, Darwin's correspondents can be grouped according to their relationship to Darwin and their function as contributors to his work. A look at a few of these various types of correspondent may help readers to obtain an overview of the Darwin collections calendared here.